Months later, she was joking that her husband had threatened to pull her out of the classes, as he found out that his now literate wife was going through his phone text messages. (Laughter) Naughty Umm El-Saad. Of course, that's not why Umm El-Saad joined the program. I saw how she was longing to gain control over her simple daily routines, small details that we take for granted, from counting money at the market to helping her kids in homework. Despite her poverty and her community's mindset, which belittles women's education, Umm El-Saad, along with her Egyptian classmates, was eager to learn how to read and write. In Tunisia, I met Asma, one of the four activist women I interviewed. The secular bioengineering student is quite active on social media. Regarding her country, which treasured what has been called the Arab Spring, she said, "I've always dreamt of discovering a new bacteria. Now, after the revolution, we have a new one every single day." Asma was referring to the rise of religious fundamentalism in the region, which is another obstacle to women in particular. Out of all the women I met, Fayza from Yemen affected me the most. Fayza was forced to drop out of school at the age of eight when she was married. That marriage lasted for a year. At 14, she became the third wife of a 60-year-old man, and by the time she was 18, she was a divorced mother of three. Despite her poverty, despite her social status as a divorcée in an ultra-conservative society, and despite the opposition of her parents to her going back to school, Fayza knew that her only way to control her life was through education. She is now 26. She received a grant from a local NGO to fund her business studies at the university. Her goal is to find a job, rent a place to live in, and bring her kids back with her. The Arab states are going through tremendous change, and the struggles women face are overwhelming. Just like the women I photographed, I had to overcome many barriers to becoming the photographer I am today, many people along the way telling me what I can and cannot do. Umm El-Saad, Asma and Fayza, and many women across the Arab world, show that it is possible to overcome barriers to education, which they know is the best means to a better future. And here I would like to end with a quote by Yasmine, one of the four activist women I interviewed in Tunisia. Yasmine wrote, "Question your convictions. Be who you to want to be, not who they want you to be. Don't accept their enslavement, for your mother birthed you free." Thank you. (Applause)
Meses después, ella bromeaba de que su esposo la había amenazado con sacarla de la clase, al enterarse de que su esposa ahora leía y escribía y que podía ver los mensajes texto de su teléfono. (Risas) Esa traviesa Umm El-Saad. Pero esto no es por qué Umm El-Saad se unió al programa. Yo vi como ella anhelaba ganar control sobre sus simples rutinas diarias, pequeños detalles que damos por sentado, desde contar dinero en el supermercado a ayudar a los niños con sus tareas. A pesar de su pobreza y mentalidad de su comunidad, donde se menosprecia la educación de las mujeres, Umm El-Saad, junto con sus compañeras de clases egipcias, ansiaban aprender a leer y escribir. En Túnez, conocí a Asma, una de las cuatro mujeres activistas que entrevisté. la estudiante de bioingeniería es muy activa en las redes sociales. Respecto a su país, conocido por acunar lo que ha denominado Primavera Árabe, ella dijo, "siempre he soñado en descubrir una nueva bacteria. Ahora, después de la revolución, tenemos una nueva cada día." Asma se refería al aumento del fundamentalismo religioso en la región, lo cual es otro obstáculo particular para las mujeres. De todas las mujeres que conocí, Fayza de Yemen fue la que más me afectó. Fayza fue obligada a abandonar la escuela a los 8 años cuando se casó. El matrimonio duró un año. A los 14 se convirtió en la tercera esposa de un hombre de 60 años, y a los 18 era madre divorciada de tres hijos. A pesar de su pobreza, a pesar de su estatus social de divorciada en una sociedad ultraconservadora, y, a pesar de la oposición de sus padres de regresar a la escuela, sabía que la única manera de asumir el control de su vida era mediante la educación. Ahora ella tiene 26 años. Ella recibió una donación de una ONG local para financiar sus estudios de negocios en la universidad. Su objetivo es encontrar un empleo, alquilar un lugar para vivir, y traer a sus hijos de vuelta con ella. Los estados árabes están pasando por cambios tremendos, y las luchas a las que las mujeres se enfrentan son abrumadoras. Al igual que las mujeres a las que fotografié, tuve que superar muchas barreras para convertirme en la fotógrafa que soy hoy. Muchas personas a lo largo del camino diciéndome qué y qué no podía hacer. Umm El-Saad, Asma, Fayza y muchas otras mujeres en todo el mundo árabe, demuestran que es posible superar las barreras mediante la educación. Ellas saben que es el mejor medio para un mejor futuro. Y aquí me gustaría terminar con una cita de Yasmine una de las cuatro mujeres activistas que entrevisté en Túnez. Yasmine escribió: "Cuestiona tus convicciones. sé quién quieres ser y no quién ellos quieren que seas. No aceptes su esclavitud. Desde que tu madre dio a luz tú eres libre." Gracias. (Aplausos)